let set18=
[
    {
        question:`#1. Consider the following statements about friction. \n 1. Heat is generated due to friction. \n 2. Kabaddi players rub dust on their hands, so that friction is increased when they try to grab their opponents. \n 3. Friction applied by fluids is called drag. \n 4. Sliding friction is less than static friction. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
        options:
        [
'A. 1, 2 and 3 only',
'B. 1 and 4 only',
'C. 2, 3 and 4 only',
            'D. 1, 2, 3 and 4',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Explanation:  Interlocking between two surfaces in contact is the reason behind friction.  In the absence of friction, we will be unable to hold a pen or pencil. It is due to friction that a matchstick catches fire on rubbing. Friction causes heat.  Kabaddi players rub sand/dust on their hands, which increases friction.,   Substances which decreases friction are called lubricants.  Water and other fluids also apply friction on the objects that move across them. Friction applied by fluids is called ‘drag’.  When an object slides over a surface, it applies sliding friction on it. Sliding friction is less than static friction.`
    },
    {
        question:`#2. Consider the following statements with respect to sound: \n 1. It can travel through solids, liquids, gases and vacuum. \n 2. The intensity of sound is measured in decibels (dB). \n 3. For the human ear, the range of audible frequencies is roughly from 20 Hz to 20,000 Hz. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
        options:
        [
'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 and 3 only',
'C. 3 only',
            'D. 1, 2 and 3',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Explanation: sound cannot travel in vacuum.The intensity of sound is measured in decibels (dB).The number of oscillations per second is called the frequency of oscillation. Frequency is expressed in Hertz. Its symbol is Hz. A frequency of 1 Hz is one oscillation per second. Sounds of frequencies less than about 20 vibrations per second (20 Hz) cannot be detected by the human ear. On the higher side, sounds of frequencies higher than about 20,000 vibrations per second (20 kHz) are also not audible to the human ear. Thus, for human ear, the range of audible frequencies is roughly from 20 to 20,000 Hz.Some animals can hear sounds of frequencies higher than 20,000 Hz. Dogs have this ability. The police use high frequency whistles which dogs can hear but humans cannot. The ultrasound equipment, familiar to us for investigating and tracking many medical problems, works at frequencies higher than 20,000 Hz.`
    },
    {
        question:`#3. Consider the following statements regarding pitch of sound. \n 1. It depends on the frequency of sound. \n 2. Birds produce high pitched sound; while the roar of a lion is a low pitched sound. \n 3. Generally, females have a higher pitched voice than males. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
        options:
        [
'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. 1 and 3 only',
            'D. 1, 2 and 3, ',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Explanation: The intensity of sound depends on the amplitude, and the pitch depends on the frequency. A higher amplitude produces a loud sound, while a smaller amplitude produces a soft sound. Similarly, a higher frequency produces a high pitched sound, and a low frequency produces a low pitched sound.Birds produce high pitched sound; while the roar of a lion is a low pitched sound. This is despite of the fact that the sound of a lion is louder while the sound produced by a bird is softer. Similarly, in instruments, A Dhol produces a sound with low frequency, while a whistle produces a sound with high frequency.`
    },
    {
        question:`#4. \n Assertion A: Utensils used to store food have a layer of tin electroplated over iron. \n Reasoning R: Tin is less reactive than iron. \n Choose the correct answer from the options given below:`,
        options:
        [
'A. Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation for A.',
'B. Both A and R are correct but R is not the correct explanation of A.',
'C. A is correct but R is not correct.',
            'D. A is incorrect but R is correct.',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Explanation: Tin utensils used to store food are made by electroplating a layer of tin over iron, because tin is less reactive than iron. Electroplating is the process of applying a layer of a metal over another by the means of electricity.`
    },
    {
        question:`#5. Assertion A: Iron used to strengthen the bridges and automated vehicles, has a tendency to be easily corroded and rusting. \n Reasoning R: To prevent the corrosion and rusting, a layer of zinc is electroplated on iron. \n Select the correct answer from the options given below:`,
        options:
        [
'A. Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation for A.',
'B. Both A and R are correct but R is not the correct explanation of A.',
'C. A is correct but R is not correct.',
            'D. A is incorrect but R is correct.',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Explanation: Iron is used to strengthen the bridges and automated vehicles. But, iron has a tendency of corrosion and rusting. Therefore, a layer of zinc is electroplated on the iron. Hence, R is not the explanation for of A; rather A is the explanation for R. The process of electroplating is used in a variety of everyday products.,  For example, some parts of car, taps in bathroom, gas burner, rim of the wheel have a layer of chromium on them. This gives them a shiny appearance and prevents corrosion.`
    },
    {
        question:`#6. Which of the following is/are correct definition of types of friction? \n 1. Dry friction resists relative lateral motion of two solid surfaces in contact. \n 2. Fluid friction describes the friction between layers of a viscous fluid that are moving relative to each other. \n 3. Lubricated friction is a case of fluid friction where a lubricant fluid separates two solid surfaces. \n Which is/are correct statement (s)?`,
        options:
        [
'A. Only 1',
'B. Only 2',
'C. Both 1 & 2',
            'D. All of the above',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Explanation: Friction is defined as the force that opposes the motion of a solid object over another. There are mainly four types of friction: static friction, sliding friction, rolling friction, and fluid,  friction. Friction and normal force are directly proportional to the contacting surfaces and it doesn’t depend on the hardness of the contacting surface. With the increase in relative speeds, the sliding friction reduces whereas fluid friction increases with the increase in the relative speed, also fluid friction is dependent on the viscosity of the fluid. Types of Friction Following are the friction types which depend on the types of motion: \n 1. Static Friction \n 2. Sliding Friction \n 3. Rolling Friction \n 4. Fluid Friction 1. Static friction is defined as: the frictional force that acts between the surfaces when they are at rest with respect to each other. The magnitude of the static force is equal in the opposite direction when a small amount of force is applied. When the force increases, at some point maximum static friction is reached. 2. Sliding friction is defined as: the resistance that is created between any two objects when they are sliding against each other. 3. Rolling friction is defined as: the force which resists the motion of a ball or wheel and is the weakest types of friction.,  4. Fluid friction is defined as: the friction that exsits between the layers of the fluid when they are moving relative to each other.`
    },
    {
        question:`#7. Which of the following is/ are not applications of Ultrasonic Waves? \n 1. For measuring the depth of Sea. \n 2. In sterilizing of a liquid. \n 3. In Ultrasonography \n 4. In sterilizing a needle.`,
        options:
        [
'A. Both 1 and 2',
'B. Only 4',
'C. Both 3 and 4',
            'D. Only 2',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Explanation: Applications of Ultrasonic Waves are: sending signals, for measuring the depth of sea, for cleaning cloths, aeroplanes, machinery parts of clocks, for removing lamp-shoot from the chimney of factories, in sterilizing of liquid and in Ultrasonography., `
    },
    {
        question:`#8. What will be the effect of temperature on speed of sound?`,
        options:
        [
'A. The speed of sound decreases with the increases of temperature of the medium.',
'B. The speed of sound decreases with the decrease of temperature of the medium.',
'C. The speed of sound increases with the decrease of temperature of the medium.',
            'D. The speed of sound increases with the increase of temperature of the medium.',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Explanation: The speed of sound increases with the increase of`
    },
    {
        question:`#9. A positive charge is moving towards a person. The direction of magnetic field lines will be in`,
        options:
        [
'A. Clockwise direction',
'B. Anticlockwise direction',
'C. Vertically upward direction',
            'D. Vertically downward direction, ',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Right Hand Thumb Rule. Thumb shows moving direction, finger encircles gives direction of magnetic field`
    },
    {
        question:`#10. What is the unit of loudness?`,
        options:
        [
'A. Bel',
'B. Phon',
'C. Decibel',
            'D. All of the above',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Explanation: The sensation of a sound perceived in a ear is measured by another term called loudness which depends on intensity of sound and sensitiveness of the ear. Unit of loudness is bel. A practical unit of loudness is decibel (dB) which is 1/10th of bel. Another unit of loudness is phon.`
    }
]